I don't know how anything
can survive out here.
This is, like, the
end of the world.
This apocalyptic scenario
we're in, it's unrelenting.
That's making this
challenge impossible for me.
You gotta last.
You gotta figure
out a way to last.
-What's that?
-It's back.
Something very bad's going on.
Something very bad's
going on right now.
Oh, my gosh.
-Holy.
-Whoa!
In a land like
they've never seen...
This is post-apocalyptic.
This isn't a place to survive.
This is a place to evacuate.
Ow!
...12 battle-tested survivalists
who have conquered
locations spanning the
globe, take on a challenge
never attempted before.
Ah!
Oh, no.
Dropped for the
first time ever...
-Dude.
-Here we go.
Look how dark that is.
...into a modern day wasteland.
It's literally like Armageddon
just happened here.
It's scorched earth.
Agh!
And they will do
it with no food,
no water, and no clothes...
-This is horrific.
-This is, like, a death march.
I am in so much pain.
...for 35 days.
Civilization left this
place a long time ago.
It is scorching hot.
And they left for a reason.
Oh, gross.
They're just falling
over dead, you know?
That's an ocean of
maggots right there.
-Oh!
This is suffering at its utmost.
To escape, they
must forge new life
from the wreckage left behind...
You need to
engineer survival here.
Made a J-hook.
No fish is gonna
break through that.
Yeah!
Now, that's a boma.
...and adapt their
primitive skills...
...to a deadly new world.
Holy.
The predators are starving,
so they are unpredictable.
They don't give up.
We're food walking through here.
This feels like the end of days.
Joe!
This place is
not built for life.
How are we gonna survive?
I do not like this at all.
Can't see anything.
We have no idea
where we are going.
Jesus Christ. This is insane.
Yeah, it is.
We have never done
anything like this before.
The longer we drive,
the more weird this gets.
I'm really nervous,
'cause I have no idea
what this is gonna
unfold for us.
Whatever it is,
it's gonna be hell.
All right, guys. Let's do it.
Whew.
-This place is dead.
-Dead.
-Yeah, yeah.
-There's nothing here.
Shelter, food, water.
There doesn't appear
to be any of that here.
-My goodness.
-Wow.
This is gonna be a challenge.
Yeah.
-What?
-Whoa.
This is insane.
I've never seen
anything like this.
Look, it doesn't look like
it's rained here in 20 years.
Look, there's ash!
There's been a fire here.
That's how dry it's been.
It feels like out here, like
an atomic bomb went off.
It's just devastated.
Yeah.
There's no shade. There's
not even a green leaf.
It looks absolutely terrifying.
-Ooh, it's dry.
-Dry, burnt, desolate.
You can smell the
ash everywhere.
Droughted out, burnt out.
What the hell happened here?
In a forgotten corner
of South Africa,
a rich and fertile land
once sustained the lives
of both animal and man.
From booming gold mine
operations of the 19th century
to vibrant farming and hunting
communities of modern day,
only to be decimated by
decades of intense drought,
mysterious disease,
and rampant wildfires
that continually lay
ruin to the area's natural
and man made resources,
leaving only a scorched wasteland,
forsaken by humans,
and haunted by the
abandoned ruins that wither
under the relentless
African sun.
Wow, this is gonna be rough.
-Let's get naked, huh?
-Let's do this.
I've never been put
in a situation like this.
When you're a naked human
being in an environment
with basically zero
natural resources,
that's a whole different
ballgame, and that's scary.
Barren, dry, hot.
There's no natural
shade in this area,
and that is a bad thing,
especially for my white skin.
-All right.
-You guys ready?
-Let's do it.
-This is gonna suck.
I can see our bags
right through here.
-Yep.
-Oh, my god.
This could be the only resources
we ever discover here.
In the face of such a
uniquely harsh environment,
each survivalist is allowed
one basic tool of their choosing...
-Got me a knife.
-Nice.
Brought my bow.
while each team receives
a pot and a fire starter.
-And I have a map.
-All right.
Looks so desolate.
There's a water source there.
-That's a long walk.
-Yeah, it is.
Oh, there's, like, some sort
of building compounds as well.
-Looks like some vehicles.
-That's so weird.
And it looks like a mine shaft?
Yeah, that's
definitely an entrance.
That looks like it's
an old medical facility.
I've never been anywhere
close to any structures.
No, me neither.
Within the 80-mile perimeter
of this vast wasteland,
the teams begin to the south
in one of four drop zones,
each with its own limited
water sources and unique
scavenge sites scattered
throughout the area,
where they'll have to search
for the discarded materials
and tools necessary to
survive the barren landscape.
Those able to endure will
have to make their way north
to escape the abandoned
zone and reenter civilization
on day 35.
The structures on this map,
which I've never seen that
in a challenge before...
there might be resources
there, and with how desolate
this environment is, we're
gonna have to be so resourceful
and use everything available
to us in order just to make it.
I know our goal is
to get to water, guys,
but if we can come up
with some quick resources
for us on the way.
-We need to ransack that.
-Yeah.
I mean, we got
some items, but...
None of the stuff that
we have is gonna put
a dent on this
environment at all.
We have to get
creative out here.
Yeah.
Well, we're in it
together now... yep.
-Let's do it.
All right, let's go.
I literally have no clue
what we're walking into.
I feel like I'm
starting this challenge
at the absolute
end of the world.
As the teams push deep
into the barren landscape,
covered in thorns and sharp
debris, daytime temperatures
will soar to over 100
degrees, only to plummet
by over 40 degrees at night.
And they'll be competing for
scarce water and resources
with ravenous
populations of lions,
hyenas, elephants,
and crocodiles,
Africa's deadliest animals,
whose aggressive behavior
grows more erratic
with each passing day
of hunger and desolation.
To the west, in drop zone one,
Steven, Alexa, and Frank plan
to investigate a deserted mine
before heading to a water source
next to a small a junkyard
of abandoned vehicles.
Wow, it is just barren out here.
There's nothing.
This is like the paths
of the River Styx.
-Yeah, Oh!
-Yeah.
You, thorn!
Ah!
-Welcome to Africa.
-This is wild.
Walking into this landscape,
the heat of this place
is insane.
The soles of my
feet are on fire.
I have ever experienced.
Guys, check this out. We
got something over here.
What? Guys, we got a mine.
No kidding.
Dude.
This area of Africa
is full of old mines,
and if there were people
there, they probably left
something behind.
It's worth going in there
for potential resources.
100% -It could have
lions, leopards, snakes.
Everything's trying to do
the same thing we're doing.
Which is, get out of
the heat and find shelter.
So, there's really
nothing more dangerous
than an abandoned
mine, except for maybe
an abandoned mine in Africa.
Look for tracks
as you go in there.
It just gets darker and darker.
Head on a swivel, look on
the ground, look above you.
Yeah.
Holy.
Well, we got
something here, guys.
-Yeah?
-What is this?
-What's that?
-Oh, it's a helmet.
A helmet.
God, was there like a war here?
Something happened.
What's that on
your left hand side?
-What is that?
-It's a wedge.
-Oh, it's a big old spike.
-...Yeah.
They used these to
drive in between rock
to like split it.
This is a weapon. Wow.
Yeah.
All right, guys, let's go.
-We need to find water.
-Yeah.
We need to start a fire.
-Oh!, -Are you
all right? Oh, no.
-Are you ok?
-Yeah.
-...that hurt.
-I bet it did... it's solid rock.
It's pretty crazy.
You know, I'm the
most experienced
survivalist out here.
Ha-ha!
I've been doing these
challenges for 10 years.
Look at that!
I've been in every feasible
environment on the planet.
And compared to
all of those places,
you can't be trained to
survive an environment like this.
This challenge right here,
it's a whole different
level of difficulty.
It's more like an end of the
world doomsday situation.
We definitely need
this canary cage.
We can make
fish hooks out of it.
We gotta think outside the box.
You have to learn by doing.
And we're about
to learn by doing.
All right, guys, we
gotta to get closer
to a water source.
Four miles to the
east, in drop zone two,
Waz, Teal, and Russell have
targeted an unknown structure
near their drop off point.
Still four miles from
their water source,
and an abandoned farmhouse.
-Oh, my gosh.
-Man, this is insane.
It is oppressive out
here. We're in an oven.
That's what this
is, it's an oven.
-Pretty bare.
-Pretty destroyed.
Given how harsh
this environment is,
that's gonna change what we
have to do in order to survive.
We're gonna have to get
some shade in a shorter time,
get some shelter
together in a shorter time.
So we're gonna have
to work pretty fast.
Hey.
I see something back here, guys.
You see over there, man?
That looks like that
building off the map.
Got a vehicle over here.
This building looks super old.
I think we need to
be careful in here.
Definitely.
Oh, this doesn't look
like anybody's been here
-for a while.
-Careful.
You never know what's
gonna be under this stuff.
Snakes, reptiles, especially,
are gonna wanna be
in something like this.
We're gonna do it
as quick as possible.
Like, whatever we can
carry today, you know?
-Yeah.
-Might be all we take.
So I'm from Australia.
I'm used to being
in dangerous places.
I was a Department
of Defense contractor.
I was training Marines,
and this is my fifth challenge.
I've spent 140 days
out here, never tapped,
never been eliminated.
My last challenge
was Last One Standing.
It was here in Africa.
I won.
Yes!
I got the PSR of 10.0
and $100,000 prize money.
But this is nothing like
any of the challenges
I've been on before.
This is post-apocalyptic
right here.
This is gonna put my
survival skills to a test
in a way they've never
been tested before.
Just wanna get this piece
of wire, 'cause I might be
able to make some,
like, a fishing hook
out of it or something.
Hey, guys!
I found some glass bottles.
-Definitely good containers.
-OK.
I need to cut this
off. It's a mud flap.
I wanna make shoes from it.
Unlike any other challenge,
we have to be way more careful
about where we're
stepping. There's glass.
There's super rusty metal.
We need to start moving.
We've got a long
way to go to the water.
OK, I wanna bring
the sheet metal.
-Y'all ready?
-Yeah.
-You good?
-That's fine, let's go.
Tell you what, I'm
feeling a little thirsty.
I don't know about y'all.
Ten miles to the
east, in drop zone four,
Amber, Joe, and Kel seek out
an abandoned medical facility
still five miles from
their targeted waterhole
near the ruins of
a hunting lodge.
-Oy.
-Man.
I gotta say, we gotta
make some shoes, guys,
'cause, uh, my feet
are on absolute fire.
This is definitely the most
difficult terrain I've been on,
and I have been in
some crappy places.
Oh, yeah!
I have almost 150
days out in the wild.
-Yeah, baby!
-We did it!
They call me a
legend for completing
a 60-day challenge.
We did it!
It's not always easy
for me and my partners.
-Trish, shut up.
-No.
You're being a dick.
But we have to be willing
-to figure it out.
-It's a caiman!
What it really boils down
to is grit, and you have
this drive inside of you
that nothing will stop you.
In your face, Amazon!
But I will say this
is the first time
I've ever been nervous
because the thought that
we could actually thrive
out here with nothing
but a barbecue pit
surrounding us, it's insane.
I say we cut up here, maybe
go check out what's on top.
Yeah, yeah.
-Oy.
-Man made steps.
Wow.
That is really scary.
-Quite questionable.
-Yeah, super questionable.
God knows what happened here.
I mean, this looks like
the nightmare-scape.
Looking at this
building, it looks old.
I don't even know
when the last time
a person was actually in it.
But there's gotta be something
in here that will be helpful
-for this challenge.
-Look at that.
Oh, that's a spear right there.
You could sharpen the end, too.
Yeah, you're coming with me.
This would be to cover my fire.
Innovation is going
to be crucial out here.
And my greatest
strength as a survivalist
is that I'm a scavenger.
That's how I've
lived my entire life.
I was widowed at 20 with
two toddlers, and I chose
to take about $500 a
month survivor's benefits.
And in order to keep us
together, we lived in camps.
And I did that alone.
Here's my girl and my boy.
I live outdoors.
I already run around naked
and poop in a hole, you know?
And I like it.
I found a half of scissors.
Oh, cool.
Because we have to move quickly,
I'm thinking, "Wow,
this wheelchair allows us
to take more than we could
just carry with our hands."
And that makes it a
force multiplier for all
the other things we're gonna do.
And so it's very efficient.
Wheel's right there.
But we're missing the bolt.
It's missing a pretty
essential bolt, like the one bolt
that's gonna keep that wheel on.
So I innovate and try
and piece together a screw
with a little wing nut that
came off of the crutch.
-Oh, you want the bearing?
-...Yeah.
-Here.
-Bearing... OK.
All right, we're good to go.
A rolling wheelchair, at least
a small conveyance to carry
some of these items
so that we're not burning
-a bunch of calories.
-Let's go, guys.
-We need water.
-It's water time.
We gotta find water.
I need a drink.
Definitely need to find water.
That's gotta be number one.
We're gonna get
roasted out here.
-if we don't get there soon.
-I know.
It's clear from the landscape
that nothing could
survive out here.
I mean, nothing is
surviving out here.
We've not seen anything alive.
Hey, guys, I see green up here.
-Yep. Yep.
-Oh, thank god, it looks like it opens up.
God.
-There's the water.
-There it is.
Definitely not a crystal
clear spring, that's for sure.
-No.
We also don't wanna set
up camp too close to water.
Yeah, everything's gonna
be coming to this... Yeah.
This is the only water
we've seen for miles.
I'm thinking we kind
of head over there,
the vehicles or
structures, whatever that is,
-maybe find some shade.
-Yeah.
-Wow, a lot of machinery.
It's like a car graveyard now,
just to add to the list
of everything that died.
Yeah, but what the hell are
these things doing out here?
There are discarded
vehicles, you know,
that have been here
for god knows how long.
It's like something
out of Mad Max.
I don't know, it looks
like home to me.
I'm somewhat of a
Florida hillbilly, and I think
with my skill set as a
survivalist, I'm gonna be
-an asset to my partners.
-Ribbit.
Being able to utilize objects
in a manner that they weren't
exactly designed for is kind
of one of my strong points.
And primitive hunting
is one of my best skills.
-That's gonna be dinner.
-Got him.
Dude!
My partner's a badass!
Being clever and just
using ingenuity in a real
survival situation.
We can make a water
purification system,
solely out of bamboo.
It's the way I find out
what I'm capable of.
Nice.
Oh my god, that is sexy.
Being out here
in this wasteland,
innovation is gonna
be so important.
It might be the difference
between completing
this challenge and failing.
All right, let's say we start
looking for a boma spot.
We got a few hours.
We need to get going.
A boma is a natural
perimeter built of sharp sticks
and thorny brush to help
prevent deadly predators
from penetrating a camp.
What is that?
-Holy...
-Oh, wow!
Look at the size of that animal.
Oh, my god.
-Jesus, he is massive.
-Here he comes.
-Look at him.
-Holy Oh, my god.
It looks like he is
coming this way.
We might wanna move back.
What the?
-Holy!
-Don't run.
Jesus! He is massive!
-Here he comes.
-...He's coming, holy.
Holy!
Ooh!
-He stopped now.
-Thank god.
Yeah.
He's moved back.
-There he goes.
-That's ominous.
Holy.
I've been to Africa on
challenges twice already.
I have never seen
an elephant so hostile.
That thing could
come in and trample us
-and go about his day.
-He's moving on.
Oh yeah, there he goes.
Wowee.
-To see that right there.
-Yeah.
Naked and
unprotected. Terrifying.
Oh yeah.
I might not have an
incredibly big survival skill set,
but I am very good at surviving.
In 2017, I died from a
routine hip replacement
on an operating table.
It's amazing when
you take it for granted,
'cause that was terrifying.
When you come back
from something like that,
you understand that...
you need to chase a
life that is nothing less
than extraordinary because
that's what you deserve.
The first challenge that I did,
I did it because I wasn't sure
-that I could.
-Spider Hunter is back!
And I think those
are the experiences
that I chase now. I covet.
-Look at that.
-Oh, my god!
I wanna see what I'm
absolutely capable of
before I come
close to that again.
This is nuts.
Now, I'm sure
we'll see him again.
If an elephant comes through
a boma with sticks and thorns,
it's not gonna stop him.
We have to beef it up.
Since the cars are here,
I mean, we could use
them as part of our boma.
Put some bumpers, some
car doors that'll lock off
this entire area here.
So what we're doing is
we're putting all of these piles
of tires and vehicles
almost in a circular structure
to make a fortified wall
to give us a buffer zone
between us and that
giant bull elephant.
I think it's gonna
be a lot of hard work,
but the clock's ticking, and
we got to build our boma
before nightfall, so
we gotta make it quick.
Nice.
-That's like a wall.
-...Yeah, it's a perfect wall.
To the east, in drop zone three,
Wes, Miranda, and Stee
have trekked five miles,
but remain one mile from
a possible scavenge site
to the north, and
a mile and a half
from their water source,
further to the west.
Oh, my gosh.
Damn it, it's hot out here.
-Mm.
-I know.
We've been walking for a while,
and you can feel that heat.
I keep scanning the area,
'cause, I mean, we are
-in the thick of lion country.
-Yeah.
There are so many dangerous
things in South Africa.
Africa is life or death,
and I mean death.
As an experienced
survivalist, I am an elite hunter.
You're the man, Wes!
I am a leader.
But with the unavailability
of resources combined
with the dangerous
game and the hot sun,
this challenge is gonna
be the most difficult one
I've ever experienced.
You need to
engineer survival here.
Yeah.
I'm gonna go sit in that shade.
And that sun is no joke.
I think we really need to
get to that water source now,
'cause everybody's dying.
At first, we were gonna
head out to a couple
of the buildings
we saw on the map.
Being able to
adapt to the situation
and change your
plan is an absolute
necessity in survival.
We've been walking for a while.
Try to get to the water
as quick as possible.
I know, we can scavenge
for additional items,
but it could also
be a distraction.
Hey, we'll keep
following you, buddy.
-Yeah.
-You can spend
a lot of time doing
that and bake in the sun
and get dehydrated.
So I don't wanna
get lured into that
before we have a shelter,
before we have a fire,
before we have clean water.
It is gonna be so important
to get to that water source.
-Yes. -'Cause we won't -last long.
-No way.
Definitely feeling
the heat out here.
Ouch!
These thorns are
quite ruthless, man.
Thorns and heat and burnt ash.
Yeah, I'm gonna
need this wheelchair,
by the time we
get where we're at.
Is that a mound up ahead,
or is that a structure?
This looks like an
abandoned building to me.
Yeah.
Let's pick it up
the pace a little bit.
Go faster.
Our trail's getting a
little tighter up here.
Yeah.
OK, my feet are
like burning, burning.
I'm all about shoes right now.
There we go.
OK.
We'll just set down
our stuff and do
a perimeter check, and not
take too long 'cause it is hot.
-Then, let's move.
-...We need to get to water quickly.
Just a wasteland here.
How sad.
Oh my goodness.
That's where black
mambas like to live.
The highly toxic venom
of the black mamba
can induce rapid
paralysis, difficulty breathing,
and heart attack.
With without prompt
treatment, its bite is
almost always fatal.
Jesus Christ.
It looks like a hunter
lived here, Joe.
That is absolutely strange.
This is not any place
I want to consider
safe and secure, so we're
going to see if there's any
little things we can carry,
and then we'll see if we can
find a place to build a
boma somewhere else.
We got a proper bush cart here.
I'm gonna make
shoes for everybody
off of these flat tires.
I have a lot of
experience in service,
from my military service
to my church service,
where I build homes.
But more importantly,
when I saw this entire
burnt landscape, I
thought, "I've done this."
Type 2 wildland firefighter.
So to work in this heat, to
work in this environment,
it's nothing new.
-Oh, shoot.
-That is so dangerous.
My previous challenge in Africa
was made hard from being alone.
I wanna tap out and go home.
I'm in a little bit
of shock right now.
Having my partner
tap out five days into it,
and having to do
it alone made it
increasingly more difficult,
but I innovated, and I strived,
and I used a strong mental game.
...-That lion's close.
Raaaahhh!
Even though this landscape
seems way more unforgiving...
, I'm losing my mind, OK.
...I can't imagine a better
way for me to prove that I have
such a high level of skill
that I can survive anywhere.
A little bit faster. Come on.
No way.
Most of this is good.
I found, I think it might
have been an old basket.
This could be made
into a fishing net.
We have a water source.
We can be catching
fish every day.
We just need some little
wire to pull it together.
But we don't have much
time. We need water.
-Oh, my god, the ground's hot.
-...Yeah, it's ridiculous.
We're gonna be getting
close to this water, I'm sure.
I am getting lightheaded
because of heat exhaustion.
I'm feeling it.
Hour after hour walking
on this terrain is just
unbearable.
But we can't stop.
We gotta get there.
'Cause I'm... every minute
I'm not drinking water,
I'm losing water.
Hey, guys, up ahead,
it's getting a lot greener.
Yeah?
Well, guys, I can see
the water through there.
It's a sight for sore eyes.
All right, let's just
push up this hill.
Gotta get this boma set up.
Gotta get some water in us.
Oh, my gosh!
Do you see that house up there?
That must be the second
building structure on the map.
Let's just see what
we can find up there.
Man, this heat just
takes it out of you.
Little woozy.
Mm.
How you feeling, Russ?
Borderline dehydrated.
I can feel the burn
behind my eyes,
and my mouth is dry.
Just stay here,
collect the shade up
-a little bit.
-All right, guys.
And rest and try and bring
that body temperature down.
Man, day one.
Talk about a bitch.
Teal and I have
this house up here
we're gonna check on.
I would love Russ
to come with us,
but it looks like he's
suffering some sort
of heat stroke or
something like that.
We do still need to find
a location for a boma.
Just be careful if there's
any snakes or anything.
Try not to touch too much stuff.
OK.
Oh, that's so creepy.
Ooh, there's a bat.
When you have bats,
in a build like this,
it's a pretty strong indication
there's lots of bacteria.
So, that's probably a real
good reason to not spend
too much time in here.
With guano, humans run
the risk of histoplasmosis,
which is a pretty
terrible disease to get.
So we're gonna selectively
pick some stuff out of here
and build a shelter elsewhere.
Breathing in fungal spores
from bat and rat feces
is known to cause
histoplasmosis in humans,
a disease that attacks
the lungs and can spread
to other organs if untreated.
-Sheet metal we can use.
-OK.
Today, we're gonna
focus on shelter and water,
'cause Russell needs some water,
or there's a chance
we lose him, you know?
I definitely want to
keep my team together.
I don't wanna lose
Russ on day one.
We're gonna do everything
we can to look after him
and try and get
him all fixed up.
I'm gonna bring you some water.
-You sure?
-Yeah.
Actually, you wanna
make me a little fire?
-I could do that.
-Yeah.
This is not gonna
happen. This is all cement.
It's like an oven down in there.
It's collected the heat
from the sun for all day.
I feel like I've been...
letting my partners down,
and I should be able to still
pull my own weight.
This is my fifth
challenge, and historically,
I've had a bit of a mouth on
me when it comes to teammates
I don't like.
You are nowhere
near the skill set to be
on something like this.
You might end up
screwing us, not doing us.
How... because I do
all the mother-work?
But I have a lot of skills
in primitive technology.
Breakfast!
And I know I can hunt
big game in Africa.
So I'm looking for
the opportunity to get
out here with my
team and kill it.
How you doing?
-I'm getting there.
-OK.
And this hellscape
is not gonna stop us.
We're on.
Sticks, sticks.
Nice job, Russell.
I gotta sit back down.
All right.
Oh, my god!
Russ, you all right?
Ah.
Russell is completely out of it.
His color is off. We're
losing him real fast.
Russell, you OK, buddy?
-You OK?
-Oh.
We need water!
Ah.
Water's on the way, babe.
We are way behind
on being hydrated.
Russell's already down and out.
He's posted up in the
shade, and he needs water.
This water's not
gonna taste great, but...
there we go.
Thank you, Teal.
It's hot, but not too hot.
Ah.
You know, I didn't think this
is how day one was gonna go.
I think I'm gonna have to
try to hydrate and just rest.
So building some sort
of protection for ourselves
from animals tonight
is the next thing
that we have to do.
Do you wanna just try to
close this in for the night?
-OK.
-It's already getting late.
And Russell ain't
going anywhere.
And Waz and I knew that
we only had each other for this.
So we just gotta build
a boma around him.
Scavenging materials
from the nearby structure,
the team will build
their shelter off of four
existing trees, using beams
and sheet metal for the walls,
then lining the perimeter
with thick, thorny debris.
The resources in
the house provide
a larger degree of
protection from nature,
but modern items are
heavy, and they're sharp.
The sun is at its highest
point, and the metal itself
is burning my fingers.
I need a more, I
need a little more.
This is definitely a lot
harder than expected.
I already know I'm
approaching my limit.
I can feel it in my body.
My hands are
shaking a little bit.
I'm getting close
to heat exhaustion.
This is torturous out here.
Ooh! This sun.
Dude, I'm really hurting.
Well, we've been
walking for a while,
-so we've gotta be getting close.
-Keep your eyes peeled.
Yeah.
I only see cows in
England, cows, and sheep.
-I see a structure over there.
-...What is it?
There's some
rubble in a building.
It looks like a pretty big one.
Do you want to spend
one minute and take a look?
-Yeah.
-Wes spots a structure.
For me, you know, my
little antennas go off like,
this is weird. It
shouldn't be here.
Maybe there's some shade.
Ton of stones, ton of blocks.
Yeah.
Well, to see how
far the water is, too,
we gotta take that into account.
Well, we gotta figure,
with this structure here,
we have to be close
to the water source,
-or they would have never put it here, right?
-Yeah.
-Yeah, that's true.
-For good and bad.
Like, every animal
that wants to kill you
is gonna be down there.
We have to have
our heads on a swivel.
Oh, hey, look
straight ahead. See?
-It is water. It is wet.
-Water!
-That is not far.
-Oh, not far at all.
-I see tracks right here.
-...Look at that.
Take a look at the
edges and kind of see
if there's any slides
from crocs... Yeah.
I mean, there's
so much at, like...
Let's be real quiet.
-A little stealthy.
-Sorry.
Growing up to 18
feet and 2,000 pounds,
an adult freshwater crocodile
can lunge out of the water
at a speed of over 20 miles
per hour and lock onto its prey
with a bite force of 4,000
pounds per square inch.
Oh, my gosh!
That's crocodile feet?
Yeah, you're right.
Everything comes to the
water, so this is already risky.
So crocs are ambush predators.
They will hide under the water.
They can jump out,
I think it's 10 feet.
It drags you into the
water and kills you.
-Just keep your eyes open.
-I am.
-Get the hell out of here.
-Yeah.
That was terrifying.
I've never been in an
area with lions and...
crocodiles.
I feel like I went
from the minors
to the majors overnight.
I'm from Florida.
I'm a charter boat captain.
I'm a professional fisherman.
I catch sharks for a living,
so I have awesome skills
on the water.
Comparing this to
my previous challenge,
Colombia was lush and
green with really nice water.
But here, this area is
in a serious drought.
We are all competing
for everything.
And the African Nile crocodile,
I mean, they have a bite force
eight times that
of a Great White.
So, for me, surviving
here in Africa
is a whole other animal.
All right, first victory!
Well done, gentlemen.
-Good job.
-Awesome job.
-We need to add to our boma.
-...All right.
'Cause things are gonna
check us out tonight.
So when they poke
their little noses in,
-we need them to get stabbed by thorns.
-Yeah.
I really want to impress
upon my teammates,
you have to protect
yourself, or you won't live
through the night.
Joe, you need any help?
I got one of the
wheels, the tread's off.
I'll get both these off,
and then we'll start moving
towards water, 'cause this is
taking the piss right out of me.
We don't have much time.
We have so much
work ahead of us.
Whoa. There's an iguana!
Right there.
It's not an iguana.
It's a monitor.
-How big is he?
-He's pretty big.
He's like three feet long.
Yeah, why don't you
grab him for dinner?
Hi, buddy!
Look at that long tongue.
Is that your burrow?
Do you live in that?
Do you need
help, or are you just
gonna talk him to death?
I just don't know if you
guys want to eat him or...
-I... if...
-Well, the thing is,
we don't have a
fire yet, so if we were
to kill him now, he's
gonna roast in this heat
and just be nasty.
And we also don't have a
way to, like, preserve him.
Till we get, like,
fire and stuff.
You wanna make a leash for him?
Take him as a pet?
No, you can't leash these guys.
They don't have a neck
that goes into a slender head.
Well, I would rather
take the risk, taking him,
and we can cook him later.
He'll rot before we get there,
and these are... these
type of lizards are...
OK, then let's just
leave him alone.
I was just getting
a vote. That's all.
I say kill him. You
say a lot of things.
-Yeah, I do.
-What do you want?
Well, I would rather
take the risk, taking him,
-and we can cook him later.
-Yeah.
He'll rot before we get there,
and these type of lizards are...
OK then let's just
leave him alone.
That's what I'm saying.
I was just getting a vote.
That's all.
As I'm just listening
to my partners banter
back and forth, it became
really uncomfortable, super quick.
I say kill him. You
say a lot of things.
-Yeah, I do.
-What do you want?
I don't want him to go to waste.
We don't know how
long it's gonna take us
to get where we're going.
OK, Kelly. Thank you.
When you are dehydrated,
you can't really eat and digest
protein without water
because it takes more water
from your body.
So I'm not gonna take
this monitor lizard's life
just to maybe
get a meal later on
that may or may
not make us sick.
Ask a simple question,
get a complicated answer
is not really something
I'm gonna have
the brainpower for in
the next coming days.
Anytime you find something
out here that you could possibly
kill and eat,
they're rare, right?
Especially in this
burned out wasteland.
And today, we
missed out on a meal.
So it's super
frustrating, but right now,
getting these tires off
is, like, my top priority.
There we go.
Dunzo!
Right now, guys, we
really gotta get out of here.
We don't have much time.
I think it's time to drop
some gear and trek to water.
-Let's do it.
-Yeah.
-Then we can come back.
-All right.
With only two hours
of daylight remaining,
the team hopes that a
waterhole a quarter mile away
will make for a viable
camp spot before dark.
We are onward to water.
So stack some tires,
kind of like bricks.
-Yeah, I like it.
-Metal fortress.
-Because of this elephant...
-Yeah, that's perfect.
Our plan is to make
a super boma now.
Yeah!
Moving these cars,
they're heavy, and they are
sharp, and they are rusty.
And we're butt
naked with bare feet.
But we gotta do something
to make ourselves
as safe as possible.
Can you get that
one hole side, Steve?
-Yep.
-Jesus.
-Ah!
-You all right?
-That gashed me.
-Oh, dude.
-That's not good.
-Let me see.
-Pretty deep right there.
-Oh, no.
Let me call the medic
and let him have
you clean it up.
Yeah, I mean, I don't
wanna be medically tapped
two days from now
because infection sets in.
I cut myself bad in one of
the dirtiest environments
I've ever been
in. It's not good.
You know, an injury
out here can turn septic
before you can blink.
Oh, yeah.
This is, kind of,
like, a wake up call.
You know, there's all kinds
of big, dangerous things
that can take you out.
But there's also a
whole lot of little things.
When night comes here,
it's gonna come quick.
It's gonna be too late to do
much of anything after that.
So we have to
get a shelter made.
Cut be damned.
Try to get this
super boma fortified.
Think we can drag that thing?
-Yeah, I think we can.
-Yeah.
We're not gonna drag it too far.
We can't go to sleep without
a fire and without a boma.
Things eat us here.
This is top priority.
Nice.
Look at that.
That big, tall green
tree right there, Joe.
I hope that's a
sign of an oasis.
We are pushing our limits.
I've never walked so
far in a challenge before,
miles and miles and
miles in the heat of the day.
It is torturous.
My skin is burning.
We literally need
to get to water.
That is the priority.
That's the one
thing we have to do.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, I see it.
It's not got a lot of
green around it, though.
No, it doesn't.
Fresh bones.
Well, we know that the
predators come here for sure.
This is some
pitiful looking liquid.
This is quite disappointing,
I have to be honest.
Look at that.
I think it's what they
burn charcoal in.
That's pretty amazing.
Farmers in the area
often converted old silos
into kilns by filling
them with burning logs
and using vents along the
side to limit the flow of oxygen,
which creates a slow
burning carbon rich charcoal
used for heating and cooking.
This thing will be hell to
pay in the middle of the day.
It's probably about 20
degrees hotter than outside.
Yeah.
I will say, Joe, we
don't have much time.
Could stay in it tonight.
We can enclose the opening.
Yeah. I mean, I'd stay there.
That charcoal kiln is no joke.
It is so hot.
There's no way
we can stay in this
as a shelter for long-term.
But there's not enough
time to get back to our items
and build another home.
So we're gonna have to
build a makeshift boma
just for tonight, and
we're gonna bed down.
Sun's about to set,
so this is definitely
pushing it to the
edge on day one.
We don't have much time.
I'm moving, I'm moving.
Right now, we're hacking
down some materials here
and stacking them
around the boma.
Kel's in there sweeping
it out nice so we, uh...
And making sure there's
no snakes and scorpions.
And then, we're gonna
have a small fire in there.
Nice.
This is gonna be
my fire pit slash...
heat bouncing wall.
It's looking really good.
Stakes tonight are
pretty high, we are clearly
right next to the only
water source for miles.
It really just put us in
a situation where we're
literally just bait
in a metal tube.
So, I mean, we
gotta protect our area,
build up the boma.
That's all we can do.
This is a brutal first day.
Starting to build
a bit of a roof in.
Just Teal and I.
It's... it's not easy.
Russell, I need
you to move, buddy.
Yeah, bud.
Russell's completely
out of commission.
Hopefully he
recovers pretty quickly,
but he is not gonna
be of any help at all.
And then we're
gon' lift this up.
It's gonna be the roof.
There isn't time to waste.
We have a lot to do
before dark, that we are just
trying our best to continue
forward at a good pace.
Let's start putting
thorns on the outside.
We're almost
completely enclosed now.
So hopefully we have proper
protection from the predators.
But in this moment, I feel
like it's become obvious that,
Russell, I need him here.
All these elements are so harsh.
We need all of our strengths
to get this accomplished.
-Is that good?
-Yeah.
Every little bit's energy
zapping, you know?
I'm in a deficit.
You're probably in a
deficit too, and Teal.
I'm close to my
limit, that's for sure.
Yeah.
I'm whooped right now.
I want that sun to go
down. I want it to be cool.
Oh, over the edge!
Oh, my goodness.
Oh, over the edge.
Oh my goodness.
What happened, Russ?
Man, I'm a little
under the weather,
so I don't know if it's
dehydration sickness or what,
but that came out with
some velocity... Yeah, it did.
I think a piece of gum I
swallowed in third grade
came up.
-You all right?
-No.
You'll be good tomorrow.
Tell you what, I'm very
appreciative of my partners,
'cause, uh...
they're definitely, uh...
holding everything
down while I, uh...
while I rehydrate and rest up.
It's just...
I don't know, my
body ain't used to this.
This place is hell.
All right, last one.
-Perfect.
-Yeah.
-Savage!
-Whoo!
-Oh, now that's a boma!
-Yeah.
How good.
It's like, a whole
new level of shade.
-Yeah, it is, hey?
-Safety.
Hell yeah.
I think, at the end of the
day, we did take a risk,
expending a lot of energy
and using up a lot of calories
moving this heavy stuff around.
But we really needed the
safety that comes from having
-a fully fortified fortress.
-Just a boma of death.
Cozy, yet terrifying.
Yep.
OK, buddy. Just watch yourself.
That's pretty damn good.
We keep lacing,
and we're home free.
'Cause our vision's closed
off by three areas now.
We can only see to the front.
I'll take this back and
just start filling, ok?
Could pop their head in there.
Nothing's coming through there.
Well done, gentlemen.
OK, so we made
it through day one.
We add a little wall
here, so the predators
hopefully stay out.
When the sun goes down,
that's when all the bad things
come out, all the things
that wanna eat you.
So we just hunker down.
We are currently
night one with the team,
and we are about
ready to ignite a fire.
Ooh, it's almost there.
-There it is.
-Nice.
-Great job, Kel.
We're using our wheelbarrow
we found in the water,
which is pretty cool,
to sustain the fire.
Night one.
The monitor lizard would
taste pretty good right now.
Oh, cold as tonight.
It was so hot at the time.
No, what?
No, Russell, come on.
I'm not with you.
I'm telling you,
there's something...
-You hear that?
-No!
Can you be more descriptive?
You're really freaking me out.
Look, it's dark, I
don't know what it is.
Oh no.
Jesus.
We think a lion,
like, really close by.
I mean, there's some noises.
And I mean, it's
really close by.
What the?
Oh, my god.
We've made it through
our first morning.
Not a lot of activity
on the water.
It's pretty quiet.
For a waterhole in
the middle of Africa,
this is pretty odd
that it doesn't have
as much traffic as it should.
This is the challenge.
The landscape, the environment,
the animals, everything is
so much harder out here.
Let's make some shoes,
'cause I don't wanna walk
around in this anymore.
Neither do I.
My feet are so
sore from yesterday,
especially with the
heat touching them.
It's like, a whole different
ballgame out here.
Our feet are tired, so
you must tire our feet.
We're gonna cut
the inside of this part
where the wires are.
OK, I got one set off.
Once that's removed, we
can adjust these to our feet.
This would be perfect.
He's got his trusty
old shoes on.
-Yeah, look at that.
-Got mine on my feet.
That's pretty, isn't it?
Let's take 'em
out for a spin here.
Oh, my god. That is...
That's kind of some
miracle wear there.
It's not 100% thorn proof,
but it definitely allows you
to move and not wear
and tear my feet down
through this black and burnt,
scorching earth
of that hellscape.
But I just don't wanna
get a blister on my foot.
Moving forward, I
think it would be nice
to not make this our home
station and to make this
-just a hunting grounds.
-Hunting and water.
-And that means less footprint.
-Yeah, that's true.
Can't leave any scent.
So the charcoal
burner is technically
a really good blind, just
because it's a water hole
that animals can drink from.
And so our presence
there definitely deters them,
so we're looking at
setting up a shelter
-at the old dilapidated building.
-To the ruins.
Through this burnt
madness, we go again.
That one made the
hairs on my arm stand up.
-Yeah.
-That was scary.
The last night, I
realized, this is real.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
What would you guys think
about using this cloud
cover and going exploring.
-100%.
-I would like that.
Like, especially if we can
find anything to put any kind of,
like, roof over our head.
We were going to plan
on just hydrating today,
but with the animals
that we heard last night,
we're gonna start
scavenging today.
We're gonna head out to
a couple of the buildings
that we saw on the map and
see if there's anything there
that we can use
to fortify our boma.
All right, I'm gonna still let
you lead, if that's cool, man.
-You're a navigator.
-That's right.
Yeah.
But looking at this
landscape as it's so barren,
I think what made me
succeed on the 21-day challenge
in Colombia was I'm stubborn.
I just wanna go, go, go, go, go.
And I think that could be
a negative effect on me,
especially now.
I've got nothing. I'm
naked with a knife.
Man, this is kind
of a creepy area.
Yeah.
Everybody makes
sure you're staying, like,
kind of stealthy, you know?
We need to be very quiet
and very wary while we're going
through this whole area.
Keep your eyes on a swivel.
That'll do.
-You good, Russ?
-What's up?
You good?
Uh, my legs keep cramping up.
I'm just trying to not, uh...
be as active to retain
some of this water
and let it get to my body.
Throughout the night, I had
severe cramping in my abdomen,
lower back, upper
thighs, and calves.
-It was insane.
-Yep.
What do you think of,
like, a little bit more rest,
a little bit more water,
build that hydration level
-back up?
-Yeah,
I feel like if I get out
and start, I'm only gonna
deplete it.
And I think I'm just
now starting to get a...
a grip on it.
-Does that make sense?
-Mm-hmm.
I'll get some fish for us today.
-I hope so.
-OK.
All -right.
I'm going back to get
a piece of upholstery.
My greatest strength
coming into this challenge
-is my bushcraft abilities.
-How to the couch.
I have ingenuity in how to
use resources in multiple ways.
As a former aircraft mechanic
in the air force, being able
to use old tools and
objects is right up my alley.
Oh, my god, go away, rain!
But my first challenge was
so cold, we had no resources
that we could truly
build a solid shelter with.
Go on! Get out of here!
But resilience is one of
the key things that you're
taught in the U.S. Military.
Look at that! Ah!
Holy cow!
But now, this is a whole
new survival challenge.
This, I wanna use
for just a protection.
The sun is probably
my number one enemy.
If I don't cover up,
I'm not going to make it
because I'm gonna end up
with sun poisoning, blister.
But last night, it got cold.
So that couch could be
used potentially for clothes,
and some degree of
protection from extreme weather.
This, I bet you it's
a piece of clothing
from the previous owners
that just got lost in the couch.
That would actually make
some really cute panties.
I got one of the pieces of wire,
made a pretty
crude looking J-hook.
It is a good looking hook.
Not bad from scratch.
You can see that's just
made up of lots of thin
wires there.
So I took one of those
strands, took that apart,
and then I did a bit
of a crude twist braid,
what I've made myself here
is a little bit of fishing line.
It's not too thick.
No fish is gonna
break through that.
I'm just gonna put these
together, see if I can't
pull one of those fish
out of that watering hole.
Hopefully it works.
We're eating fish
by the end of the day.
I got faith in you, Waz.
I just have to say
that this walk is
so much easier with shoes.
This shoe needs
some reworking here.
It's cutting my feet.
-Oh, look at this, guys.
-Oh, look at that!
-Dude, it's a big tree.
-Mm.
It's a perfect area for a boma.
It's got some little
natural shading right here.
Yeah, this seems pretty good.
It's got half a tree
right here, ready for us.
We can build around it.
I was thinking,
make a tight A-frame
with a corrugated metal.
So we're coming off
of this branch, right?
-That's kind of the idea?
-Mm-hmm.
-Run a cross beam
and then start
sheeting off of that.
-Perfect.
-Yeah, yeah.
I think that's a good idea.
The plan for today is to build a
comfortable and secure boma
so we can utilize
that metal tube
for what it's really
best potential is,
and that's getting
us some protein.
Within 50 yards
of the abandoned hunter's
house and a quarter mile
from their water source,
the team plans to use
salvaged materials to build their
shelter off a large mapani tree,
repurposing fence
posts and rafter beams
to create a basic A-frame,
then layering on old roofing
sheets of corrugated
metal to enclose it.
-All right.
-Let's do it.
We can put this in the
center of our A-frame.
That'll be great.
We'll just drag it over
and start our piles.
The only concern I have
right now is we're expelling
so much energy
to build this boma
in the heat of the day.
It's risk versus reward.
I'm trying to get the low
hanging fruit right now,
just stuff that's kind of loose.
Quite a lot, but, you
know, some of it's tough.
Yeah? Be careful for that.
Literally stepping on a bunch
of barbed wire in the ground.
Just, you need to
go right behind the...
wherever the path is.
I think my eyes are attuned
to pokies in the ground here.
Yeah, those ones
are, a little bit different.
Yeah, I know, well...
I got the shoes.
I'm good.
Joe doesn't really seem
interested in my opinion.
It's the Joe Show
at the moment, so.
Do we bring any cordage?
Uh, no, that was breaking.
Think got wire
on the... on the...
-On the wheelchair.
-...The other stuff was not very strong.
Well, if you guys
wanna be hardcore,
probably hopefully...
There's some wire
right here at the base of
this tree, behind you, Joe.
There's a bunch of wire mesh.
We haven't got any of that.
I'm gonna ask you to
not interrupt me, please.
Like, in the middle of talking.
You do talk a lot,
so it's hard to get
a word in, edgewise,
just so you know.
I was just pointing this out
in case you wanted to get it.
You can say yes, I understand,
or no, I will interrupt you
-whenever I feel like it.
-Well, I don't know.
You're kind of an interrupter. I guess
we're just gonna have to deal with that.
-Kelly.
-I'm getting used to it.
Kelly, when I'm talking,
can you not interrupt me?
-Are you seriously gonna keep asking that?
-Yeah.
OK, I'm just not gonna talk,
because I can barely
get a word in edgewise,
with you anyway, so.
Great, thank you.
Ugh.
Jesus Christ.
OK, I'm just not gonna talk
because I can barely
get a word in edgewise,
with you anyway, so.
Great, thank you.
Ugh.
Jesus Christ.
After this interaction
with Joe, I just feel like
I can't be comfortable
around him
if he's gonna snap like that.
But he does talk a
lot, and maybe he's just
stressed out 'cause
these conditions
are pretty relentless.
So I just put that behind me,
and I just keep moving forward,
and right now
it's not important.
I think I'm gonna go get nails.
I'm gonna rake.
I'm gonna take
stuff out of here first.
Not having that. Definitely not.
I gotta be honest.
I was a little disappointed
seeing the tension
between my team.
I got Joe, I got Kel,
and they're so different
in personalities,
but we got 35 days.
There is no renting
another condo over here
or a room over here.
We are stuck together
like glue, so we need
to make this work.
She doesn't make
any sense to me.
You know, I'm just trying to set
a healthy boundary with this.
I'm just trying to say,
"Hey, look, I don't appreciate
"you just cutting me off when
I'm in the middle of talking,
when I'm in the middle
of explaining something."
And then what I got back
from her was a whole lot
of negativity and a
whole lot of blaming me,
so it's really aggravating.
You know, 'cause this
is a tough environment.
And if she continues to
do it, she's not gonna really
help us in our survival.
Yeah, it's frustrating.
It's very frustrating.
Is there a vulture circling?
Yeah, we got a few
vultures up there.
I don't know why
they're circling over us.
-That's not a...
-Is there something anyone wants to say?
Did we survive
last night, or...?
It is morning of day
two. Armageddon.
-All right, you guys ready?
-Yeah.
-Let's do it.
-Let's go.
We're still acclimating
to our environment.
We're still kind of figuring
out the lay of the land
and what we need to
do to actually survive.
So we'll do a quick scout,
walk around the area,
see if we can't find
any animal sign.
Guineas.
Oh, yeah.
Look at that.
Warthog den, maybe?
Maybe porcupine.
Don't seem like anything's
been here for a while.
Yeah
Absolutely... Yeah, let's
do a quick walk around.
I mean, if I was a guinea,
I would lay my eggs here.
-Right?
-Hands down.
That's what you'd think.
Guinea fowl pretty much
running the same trails every day.
So I know the guinea's
come right through here.
So many places to
hide them around here.
Mm-hmm.
They seem to like...
under the trees.
-Oh, lookie here, eggs.
-Oh, they are there!
-Guinea Eggs.
-Epic!
-Perfect.
-Huh.
-How good.
-We get food.
-How crazy is that?
-Oh, my god.
There were two
eggs sitting right there.
And eggs are protein.
And this is the first
food that we have found.
And this is huge.
You guys ready for some
African eggs Benedict?
Yes.
All right. First African meal.
-I'm so excited.
-We got one floater.
Oh, no.
Does that mean it
has a baby bird in it?
Um... we'll find out
here in a minute.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm sort of more of a
vegetarian at heart, so
fetuses are not my
idea of a good time.
Is that a head
with an eye on it?
Right there, yeah.
That's definitely a
head with an eye on it.
It's a very small baby bird.
Oh, no.
-Take a bite first.
-Bon appetit.
Delicious?
You're going to have the...
No, you can have
the fetus if you want.
Fetus it up.
These eggs are the weirdest eggs
I have ever eaten in my life.
But look, out here
in this landscape,
food isn't guaranteed.
And I can't take the
chance that if I don't eat this
and we don't find
something else to eat,
I'm not gonna starve.
Oh, the shimmy shakes.
Like taking a
shot of bad tequila.
That's just weird.
It's kind of like zombie eggs.
Nothing about an egg
is supposed to have, like,
-bones in it.
-Yeah.
Oh, there's
something huge ahead.
I mean, what in the world?
If it wasn't so damn far
from the water, it'd look like
a good place to stay.
-I don't know.
-Holy!
Look at the size of
that kudu! Oh, my gosh!
It almost looks like
it's an old farmhouse.
This place is creepy
as hell, and it's far away.
So the quicker we can scavenge
and get the heck out of here,
the better it is for me.
All right, let's go
room by room.
So we start in the corner,
-go from left to right?
-Yeah.
It's really important
here to keep vigilant,
keep your eyes open.
Oh, watch all these nails.
There's a bunch
of nails poking out.
Well, I tell you what, we
have actually enough tin
right here that we have a
roof. I'm telling you what.
We're gonna have
to get back soon.
Sun's high in the sky.
We've still got to be very
conscious of our time.
-Yeah.
You know my big concern
with the middle part of the day?
The sun will bake you to
death and give you dehydration,
and we still have to get all
the way back to our boma.
So we have to stay laser
focused on what we're doing.
-You guys are incredible.
-I'm here for it.
Hey, the sun is hot.
Yeah, so let's get out of here.
Um, are we
dismantling this fabric?
Last piece, and then
we got a whole ass.
Ok, here. Oh, this
is good cordage.
-Yeah.
-Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, hey.
I know, I know,
Dad. Don't yell at me.
All right. Keep it together.
-Take away your allowance.
-I know, I know.
Steven and Miranda
have such lack of focus.
-Yeah, we need some focus.
-Almost there.
Ok.
At least, you won't
be shivering later.
All right, should we get out of
here, won't you make haste? ...Yeah.
Yeah, I think Wes
loves that idea.
We need to hydrate, you know?
We've got to get back
and get some water,
or we're gonna be
in a bad situation.
Sorry, all right, we're going.
OK, so everything's
normal. Everything's fine.
There's quite a few ripples
that I see moving around,
especially as I
start to approach
this water hole here.
I know there's fish in here.
I just have to find a
way to get them to bite
my little homemade
hook that I have there.
There's a bit of
moisture in this area,
so there might be something
like a fire, maybe an insect,
or things I can use as bait.
Check under everything we
have here and see what's available.
I think I can see
a scorpion in here.
Let me just...
Yeah, that looks good.
I don't wanna lose him,
'cause this guy's gonna be
good bait.
I'm just gonna get his
stinger off the end here.
This is something juicy that
those fish are gonna love.
We're limited to
about eight feet...
of cord on this.
So, what I'm gonna do...
is I'm gonna leave
this as a passive line.
There's every chance I can
grab something overnight.
All right, we'll
leave it for now.
Hopefully that comes up
with something overnight.
I'm gonna go try and
get some firewood.
I've got a skirt.
I've got some paperclip
things that I made for my skirt
to keep it up.
And then, of course, I've got
my top from that dolly shirt.
This stuff protects
me from the sun,
but also stay warm at night.
-You doing OK?
-I feel better.
We need the pot refilled.
And I'm gonna be
totally honest with you,
-I don't feel a hundred percent.
-Oh yeah, I figured you didn't.
I can go do it.
But if I take it nice and
slow... I wanna try to hunt.
I'm feeling a lot better
than I did, so might as well
just get out there and
fill our bellies, you know?
Get out there and do what we do.
Hey, Teal, I saw down a
ways a nice little herd of impala
Wind's going that way, so if I
can get down yonder and around,
I should be able to
possibly get a shot off.
Yeah, I mean, every
try is a good try.
Exactly.
This is definitely an
opportunity for me to prove
that I can survive with
my teammates out here
and kill it, and whatever
I gotta do to help.
Russell is making time
for things that excite him,
like, uh, hunting.
I feel like that's the only
thing that he's up for.
All the mundane but
absolutely necessary stuff,
we are doing on our own.
Man.
There's just such devastation.
With this environment looking
as bleak as it is and it being
as burnt as it is, it's
pushed the wildlife out.
And we're gonna have
to go look for that wildlife.
This place has no canopy.
Everything's burned.
So hunting here, it's
a little intimidating.
I'm seeing a lot of tracks
coming right through here.
That's all hunting is. You
gotta learn your target.
What they do, how they move,
when they get up, when they go
to sleep, when they
eat, when they drink.
I see all these fresh
tracks in this riverbed.
Can't win them all,
can't win them all.
Tell you what,
I got close, close.
A miss is a miss.
It is what it is.
But I know my stalking game
is good, but I can only do it
for so long before I
start getting beat down.
Just the walk
itself wore me out.
-Hey, he's already back.
-Hey, y'all.
-That was fast.
-What you get, buddy?
Bud, I got about 25, 30 yards
-from those two females.
-Yep.
I closed in the distance
all the way up until
we got into that brush,
where I was making it difficult.
But I wrapped off
one, but I hit a branch
and it reflected it
down into the riverbed.
-So...
-That's awesome.
Yeah, it's very awesome.
You know what else we could do?
Since the pot is empty, we
could just go to the water.
There you go.
And see what that's like today.
Yeah, I'm happy with that.
I'm gonna have to take a sitter
just for a couple of minutes.
I didn't know how
worn out I was.
Yep.
As far as Russell goes,
he's using a lot of resources,
and he's not contributing
anything back in.
And Teal and I are
putting in a lot of extra effort
that we wouldn't have
to if he wasn't here.
It's difficult for
us to get through,
especially when
we're not eating.
It's difficult for us to look
after a whole 'nother person.
So we're gonna need to
work something else out.
-We're in.
-Golden.
For this challenge,
thankfully, I brought my axe
because we're using it
right now to help build
-our second shelter.
-Yeah, that's good.
-Is it?
-Yeah.
Nailed it.
We got enough to
get a basic A-frame up.
We're getting our
frame up right now.
Next step, we're gonna use
some of that corrugated metal
as rooftop material.
-Yeah, about right there.
-We need 10 total.
I can go get more.
-Oh, okay.
-That looks great.
-I think that's a good start.
-Yeah.
We got a lot more work
to do here, get this place
safe from predators at night.
So right now, we're still
planning to stay at the pond
in the night because
that shelter in boma
and that security that we
have there is established.
All right, let's go.
But once this
shelter's finished,
we're gonna move up here
permanently, and that's gonna
give us the advantage of
making that watering hole
just strictly a hunting ground.
Rugged Joe says it's
time to Rugged Go.
Holy crap.
Man, this was a
huge undertaking.
-Yeah.
-I hope it pays dividends.
In this wasteland, even though
we can use man made items,
going to the farmhouse
sacrifices a lot of calories.
I mean, it takes you a
good hour to get there
through rough terrain.
Then you've got to
hump it all the way back.
Oh my gosh, we're home.
And so right now,
the work required
getting a roof on our
place, it's just too much.
Man, that was a hike.
So tomorrow morning,
we have to focus on getting
something over our heads.
Wes, thank you for, like,
keeping us somewhat,
'cause I feel like me and
Steve are the same way,
like, "Oh, my god!"
You do. It's like herding fleas.
But, like, I appreciate you,
'cause I like that you keep us
-level-headed.
-Well, I like you guys.
I think we make an awesome team.
-Yeah.
All right, I need to work
on my fish net, get it done.
It's worth a shot to try to
see if there's any fish in there.
I'm gonna put some
bone inside of that.
I've been sewing
the top of this and just
tightening it down,
I gotta fix that side.
We got this at the medic place.
It's a bunch of copper wire,
which is super soft to use.
So I've been using pieces
of this to fill this hole.
One little hole
can let them all out.
Ever had to sew with a wire?
It's not fun.
Gotta think outside the
box to survive out here.
I'm gonna be open
minded and set this up,
and there will be fish.
I'm gonna say that.
There will be fish.
They're gonna go in this trap.
Right now, my concern
is the relationship
between Joe and Kel.
This is just the beginning.
They're already fighting.
I just want everybody
to get along right now.
Maybe there's a
chance I can fix this.
We haven't had food
yet, and I don't want this
to get any worse.
So, we're gonna see if
we can get some crawfish,
who knows what's in there.
So how are we gonna
funnel the top of it?
Well, we found this
gold panner's little...
where they would sift through
the sand, and dirt and clay
and all that to find gold.
There's a little hole there.
And then we're gonna
literally weave this
on the top like this.
It'd be really sad not to
get a fish here in Africa.
Using the same principle as
a primitively woven cone trap,
Amber's modified basket
will use bait to draw fish
through a hole in the mesh top.
Once inside, they
become too disoriented
to find their way out.
-OK guys, good luck.
-All right.
-Food.
-Yeah.
Breakfast.
I hope it's fruitful
and we can get
some fish out of it.
It is so imperative that
we have food by day three.
Very quickly, you
can go downhill
without food in your system, so,
I will do whatever it
takes to get us food.
There's gotta be
something in this water.
I don't know what,
but something.
All right, fingers crossed.
I took the back.
I really don't
need a power point
to explain to me fire.
No one here will understand you.
Yep.
I don't understand
this, I'm like, "It's so hot,
then it's freezing."
Yeah, there's no
heat from the fire.
Yeah.
All right, so we're in the
middle of African bush,
and we got a seamstress
school going on over here.
But I tell you what, the
ingenuity of being able
to make a blanket
from, what is that?
The inner parts of a bench
seat from an old sixties model
Chevy, like C10 pickup.
And since we found a
couple eggs, I think...
I can make a trap with
this canary cage we got
from the old mine.
So my plan is, I got a
trigger stick right here.
I'm gonna put bait
on this quad hook.
Bird comes in here,
grabs the bait,
shuts himself in.
So I'm gonna kind of camouflage
a little bit so it doesn't look
exactly like a birdcage.
I got a piece of
grasshopper, a little bit of bait.
See if it works.
It should.
Oh, look at that.
Last night, I had no
idea what was going on.
It woke me up, I was like...
-It was... it was not cool.
-All I heard was,
"Stop talking!" And then
you said, "Stop talking."
And I was like, "What
is going on here?"
He's like, "What are you doing?
You just poked
me with the thorns!"
Grabbed it, ripped
it, and threw it.
And just, "Why don't
you stop talking?"
And it's just evil.
It's like, "Oh my god, I
never wanna see you again.
"This sucks.
I have 32 more days with you."
I intended on surviving
all of the hardships
that I'm in right now with
the burns and the dehydration
and the thorns, but I
didn't plan on being stuck
in a tube with
someone like that.
I just don't have the
patience for Kelly.
You know, I just... I
can't I understand, she...
last night, she hits me
in the head with a stick,
moving around in the dark.
I say, "Hey," she
then does it again.
And it's just excuses, man.
It's just more and more excuses.
Instead of, "I'm
sorry," that's it.
That's all you have to say.
We're all still human beings,
so treat us accordingly.
I need to get a fire started.
You think, Russell,
you're going to be up
to collect some firewood?
Yeah, I don't know.
-I don't feel like risking it.
-OK.
I won't lie.
I've had some internal
dialogues with myself
that have been about wishing
that Russell was not sitting
and wishing that he was
helping because I'm exhausted.
The heat is really getting
to me, and I keep going,
so why can't he?
He seems to put
efforts in to things
that he wants to do, but
then and he's not putting
any efforts into what
the team needs him to do.
Like he did not
collect any firewood.
He's never come to
get water, boiled water,
pretty much anything
that we're doing to help us
as a team survive,
he just hasn't done.
The two of us can't babysit
him the rest of the time.
It's not OK, and I
completely see it.
Even as a middle person,
it's important for him
to even understand
somebody saying, "Hey dude,
what you're doing is
completely out of line."
This is definitely gonna
be a hindrance for us,
and I don't know how
much Kel is gonna take,
and I don't want Kel to leave.
-It's definitely not OK.
-It's not.
I have no intentions
of leaving, but...
And right now, they're stuck
together, and I don't know
how to do that. It's huge.
It's huge.
If he doesn't come to start,
you know, sharing the
workload, I honestly don't know
if I have the strength... Yep.
...to make it for 35 days.
35 days is really
long time to survive
in conditions this harsh.
And I think it's gonna be
really difficult to make it
there if we're
carrying somebody.
Last night was uncalled
for, and it keeps happening
and getting worse,
and it's obviously
just not gonna work.
You know, a whole lot
of things have to change.
I didn't plan for an asshole.
This place is a disaster area.
Mother nature has destroyed
it, and we will not make it
35 days with this
tension between my team.
It's just making me
think that there's no way
back from this.
We need to do this together.
We need all of our strengths
to get this accomplished,
because here, the
worst is possible.
We have to survive
together as a team.
If we don't, how in the
hell are we gonna make this
in this wasteland?